Guide to the Clarence Louis Frank Gohdes Papers, 1811-1990s and undated (bulk 1905-1981)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject Files Series, 1857-1969 and undated, bulk 1915-1969 (Box 6)
  Inspired by the UNESCO translation project, Gohdes initiated a survey of leading American literature critics and scholars in 1949 to determine the best twenty American books. Gohdes and his fellow committee members, Jay B. Hubbell and Lewis Leary, successfully polled approximately twenty-five people. Those polled include many major critics of the day: Ralph Rusk, Walter Blair, Henry Canby, Mark Van Doren, Fred Lewis Pattee, F. O. Matthiessen, Van Wyck Brooks, Clarence Gohdes, Jay B. Hubbell, Charles Anderson, and Henry Nash Smith. Files includes correspondence from these critics discussing and listing their choices for the best twenty American books. The survey seems to have been passed on to UNESCO, and was used for publicity for the American Literature Section of the Modern Language Association by submitting the final tallied poll to newspapers and journals. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bibliographies (Box 6)
    - General, 1940-1956 (Box 6)
    - Regional, 1963 (Box 6)
  - Contemporary poetry (Box 7)
    - Criticism and reviews, 1915-1924 and undated (Box 7)
    - Introductory lecture, University of Wisconsin, [Lewis Chase?], 1917 and undated (Box 7)
    - Possible publishers for contemporary poetry, 1917 and undated (Box 7)
    - Student notes and papers, 1928 and undated (Box 7)
    - A student's anthology, undated (Box 7)
    - Selections, undated, (7 folders) (Box 7)
  - Modern poetry, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Poetry, 1924 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Russian studies of American literature, bibliography (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 7)
    - General, 1968 and undated (Box 7)
  - Travel narratives and the West, 1857-1956 and undated, (1-3 of 4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Travel narratives and the West, undated, (4 of 4 folders) (Box 8)
  - UNESCO/ American Literature Section's Best American Books List, 1948-1949 and undated (Box 8)
    - Organizational correspondence, 1948-1949 and undated (Box 8)
    - Survey results, 1949 and undated (Box 8)
  - Vernon Parrington Syllabi, 1923 (Box 8)
    Obtained from a former student of Parrington, one of the most influential critics and historians of American literature.
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1851-1990s and undated, bulk 1930-1987 (Box 8)
  Consists of two subseries: Writings by Gohdes and Writings by Others.
  - Writings by Gohdes Subseries, circa 1953-1992 and undated (Box 8)
    Consists chiefly of unpublished stories and memoirs as well as published writings. Also included are several academic pieces (other academic writing, such as lectures, can also be found in the Author Files Series). The manuscripts include work Gohdes did on an anthology, "True Stories about Indians from St. Nicholas Magazine and The Youth's Companion." Materials related to this project include original introductory material written by Gohdes as well as marked-up pages from the two magazines indicating which stories he hoped to include.
    Notes and notecards pertain to Gohdes's more formal projects, while others provide insight into his many different interests. For example, a datebook contains "Some notes on big trees," which concern early literary references to large trees in the United States. Included is a notebook containing Gohdes's research on American humor. There are notes for a proposed project, "A Series on American Argument for Peace," containing very rough bibliographic notes on possible entries.
    The Printed Materials consist of reprints of published articles by Gohdes, and include pamphlets and circulars that advertised the many series and books that Gohdes edited, introduced, or authored.
    Arranged alphabetically by title within each section.
    - Manuscripts (Box 8)
      - "American Geography and American Literature," 1960 and undated (Box 8)
      - "Centennial of Leaves of Grass," 1955 (Box 8)
      - "The Christmas Cherry Tree," undated (Box 8)
      - "An Elementary Interview: A Satiric Farce in One Act," undated (Box 8)
      - "A Glossary of Selected Critical Terms," circa 1953 (Box 8)
      - "Jay B. Hubbell," 1977 (Box 8)
      - Notes and notecards, undated, (5 folders) (Box 8)
      - "On Hearing Bad News in the Perkins Library," 1992 (Box 8)
      - "Our Robert Frost Indian: A Tale Partially True," 1987 (Box 8)
      - Story selections, undated (Box 8)
      - "True Stories about Indians from St. Nicholas Magazine and The Youth's Companion," undated (Box 8)
        - Introduction and prefatory materials, undated (Box 8)
      - "The Way It Was," undated (Box 8)
    - Printed materials, 1930-1987 and undated (Box 8)
      - A-L, 1930-1967 and undated (Box 8)
      - M-Z, 1936-1987 and undated (Box 8)
  - Writings by Others Subseries, 1851-1990s and undated (Box 8)
    Chiefly contains articles and reprints that were sent and inscribed to Gohdes by his students and colleagues. The only manuscript materials are poems by Gohdes's one-time student, Kiffen Hayes. Several other pieces, not inscribed, comprise the rest of the subseries, including Norton's Literary Almanac for 1852 Containing Important Literary Information. The incomplete inventory of printed materials in the Gohdes Papers, created by a Duke University archivist, gives bibliographic information for many of the items. After the inventory, folders are arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Inventory of printed material, 1990s (Box 9)
    - Adams, Raymond, 1932 (Box 9)
    - Author unknown, 1958 (1942) (Box 9)
    - Baum, Paul, 1931 (Box 9)
    - Bestor, Jr., Arthur E., 1948 (Box 9)
    - Camus, Albert, 1957 (Box 9)
    - Clark, Harry Hayden, 1953-1955 (Box 9)
    - Damon, Ethel M., 1935 (Box 9)
    - Day, Cyrus, 1958 (Box 9)
    - Eltron, William, circa 1949 (Box 9)
    - Frenz, Horst, 1945 (Box 9)
    - Goldwater, Walter, 1963 (Box 9)
    - Hayes, Kiffen, 1971 and undated (Box 9)
    - Herron, Ima Honaker, 1987 (Box 9)
    - Hubbell, Jay B., 1922 (Box 9)
    - Jones, Jr., Arthur E., 1950 (Box 9)
    - Liljegren, S. B., undated (Box 9)
    - Mabbott, Maureen Cobb, 1981 (Box 9)
    - Meriwether, James B., 1963-1964 (Box 9)
    - Norton's Literary Almanac, 1851 (Box 9)
    - Pizer, Donald, 1965 (Box 9)
    - Schneidau, Herbert N., 1968 (Box 9)
    - Thompson, Lawrance, 1938 (Box 9)
    - Wellek, René, 1961 (Box 9)
    - White, William, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Wood, Gordon R., 1961 (Box 9)
- Scuppernong Series, 1811-1984 and undated, bulk 1977-1984 (Box 9)
  Gohdes, an avid gardener throughout his life, wrote a definitive historical and cultural study of the scuppernong, a white grape of the American South. The series contains Gohdes's extensive research and writing materials pertaining to this book, The Scuppernong, North Carolina's Grape and its Wines. These materials are divided into three subseries: Correspondence, Research and Notes, and Publication Materials.
  Within folders, items are arranged chronologically by date.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1979-1983 and undated (Box 9)
    Contains Gohdes's queries for information on the scuppernong and agricultural production in North Carolina and the United States. Many letters exchanged with North Carolina vineyards and various organizations possessing information about viticulture or the scuppernong comprise the majority of the correspondence folders.
    - 1979 Jan.-1980 Apr. (Box 9)
    - 1980 May-1983 July and undated (Box 9)
  - Research and Notes Subseries, 1811-1984 and undated (Box 9)
    Gives insight into the extent of Gohdes's preparation for Scuppernong. The "Articles and Essays" folder contains many photocopies of essays including a fair amount of material on Secondo Guasti, a Californian wine-grower, and on Garrett and Company, an American winery. The "Printed Materials" folders consist mainly of brochures and pamphlets relating to the agriculture and science of grape production in the American South, many of which were published by government- or university-sponsored organizations. Also part of the subseries are several folders of notes, mainly on index cards, as well as folders on the two Garrett brothers (owners of a North Carolina winery), and Duplin Wine Cellars, another local vineyard.
    - Articles and essays, 1811-1983 and undated [earliest dates are photocopies of originals], (1 of 2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Articles and essays, 1811-1981 and undated [earliest dates are photocopies of originals], (2 of 2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Duplin Wine Cellars, 1977-1984 and undated (Box 10)
    - Fred Garrett, 1934-1983 and undated (Box 10)
    - Paul Garrett, 1977-1979 and undated (Box 10)
    - Notes, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10)
    - Printed materials, 1901-1983 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Publication Materials Subseries, 1980-1982 (Box 10)
    Includes several reviews and clippings following the book's publication, as well as materials from the publisher, Duke University Press. In the Press folder can be found an "Author's Questionnaire" filled out by Gohdes.
    - Duke University Press, 1981-1982 (Box 10)
    - Reviews and clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 10)
- Clippings Series, circa 1922-1970 and undated (Box 10)
  Clippings not originally filed in the Author Files Series have been included in the Clippings Series. It contains clippings on Omar Khayyam, The Thoreau Society, Upton Sinclair, an editorial on Sinclair Lewis's death, the history of American Literature, Celestine Gohdes's orchids, and Mary Clair Sinclair. Items are arranged chronologically by date.
  - Circa 1922-1970 and undated (Box 10)
- Oversize Materials (Box 10)
  - Authors Files Series, 1905, 1950 (Oversize-box 1, Box 10)
    - Eliot, T.S. (Box 10)
      - Phonograph recording of Eliot reading selections of his poems, 1950 (Box 10)
        Technical Services needs to reformat for use copy before use.
    - Twain, Mark (Box 10)
      - 70th Birthday Souvenir Supplements, 1905 (Box 10)
  - Writings by Gohdes Series, undated (Box 10)
    - Story selections, undated (Box 10)